Alright guys, we are up to the actual coaching,
instructing and demoing exercise,
and we're going to talk about the different types of cues there are.
So, why is effective exercise demonstration important?
It's not just about doing a squat,
making sure they're watching. and then expecting them to do it themselves.
It's a lot more in depth than that.
So, obviously the biggest importance is clear understanding of the form.
One thing I need you to take away from these modules guys is that
our clients are beginners and for them,
they're extremely overwhelmed and unsure of how to do these exercises.
Some may have done training in the past.
For a lot of them, this may be their first time doing a squat
or a bench press. For us,
it's hard to even fathom that but for them,
that's their reality and they literally don't know anything and that's why we exist,
okay. So, it's really important to understand to help them visualize the proper technique,
understand the proper technique and help them learn it as quickly as possible.
Of course, it's important for preventing injury.
We have to make sure we're showing them how to do it properly.
Common feedback we get from clients is that what they like about us is
that they know when they watch us do technique.
It's the right technique. A common reality for a lot of them is that
when they've been to gyms in the past, they've watched random strangers in the
gym doing wrong technique, then they do the wrong technique and then they hurt
themselves. And last one,
it helps them feel more confident, you know,
seeing someone do the exercise properly.
And correctly, that makes sense for them in person,
helps them feel more confident and just enjoy training more.
Now how do we demonstrate effectively?
Well, the first thing is you have to demonstrate the exercise yourself,
of course. Now we always demonstrate an exercise when it's the client's first time
doing it. Always,
every time it's a new exercise, even if we think they're competent,
you never know. Obviously, you want to perform it and making sure they're watching.
They can watch from any angle you prefer,
they can walk around, whatever they would like.
You would explain the key points. And this is what we're about to go
through, the different types of cueing.
You're going to highlight important aspects of form and execution in a
really easy, digestible way that they can understand.
And lastly, encourage questions and feedback.
Allow them to ask questions, no matter how difficult or silly they are.
Give it a space, give them a space where they can open these questions,
clarify any doubts. Now internal cues guys,
we've got two types of cues, internal and external.
Internal focuses on body sensations,
the inside of the body, you know, feel your muscles working.
These can be feel your lats stretching on the way up on a pull
down or feel your chest squeeze at the top of a cable fly.
These are great for internal body awareness,
however, this is overwhelming for beginners.
These are more suitable towards intermediate and advanced lifters.
cues relate to the outcome or an external object or part
of the environment, such as drive your hips forward or push
the ground away. This is about the desired end result.
benefits of external cues External cues is that it makes movements better.
It leads to more efficient and effective movements,
specifically with our clients who are beginners.
The reason is, internal cues are overwhelming.
Our beginner clients already don't really know what body parts do and where they
are and what they do.
If you say, I want you to squeeze your chest together,
or I want you to feel your lats stretch on the way up,
they have no idea what that means, they get overwhelmed and they get confused.
Versus, if you say,
let your arms stretch up to the sky,
or drive your elbow into the ground,
or drive your elbow to the wall behind you.
Or, push the ground away, it's easier for them to comprehend and
understand, which leads to them just doing better technique.
enhances performance too, because instead of overthinking,
I'm not feeling it in my lat, where is the lat,
I can't feel it. It's related to an exercise.
And it just makes it easier to understand and apply.